welcome to the listening Time Podcast
hey everybody this is Connor and you're
listening to episode
131 of the listening Time Podcast today
we're going to talk about a topic that I
love it's one of my favorite topics and
I think that this episode is going to be
very interesting for you we're going to
talk about English pronunciation
so this is a very relevant topic for all
of you because if you're listening to me
this means that you're learning English
so
pronunciation is probably the element of
English that is talked about the least
it's probably the element that is the
least focused on when you learn English
with a teacher or in school
pronunciation is a hard topic especially
English
pronunciation but I love it it's one of
my favorite aspects uh of teaching
English as you can probably tell by now
especially if you've joined my
membership because uh you've seen that I
uh do a lot of training in practice with
the sounds of English so I really like
this topic and I want to talk about
English pronunciation in general and
about the
difficulties uh with
pronunciation and about how you can
improve your pronunciation so this
should be a great topic for today before
we start remember to join my us
conversations podcast if you want to
start practicing with real conversations
between me and other Americans this is
what you need if you can already
understand me pretty well and you need
to reach that next level where you can
understand any native speaker when
they're talking to you or when they're
talking to other people so if you want
to join that you can click on the link
in the episode description below this
episode that's
patreon.com USC
conversations and don't forget to join
my membership and specifically if you
become a listening time super member or
any of the higher tiers then you'll get
my pronunciation training you'll get my
pronunciation seminars where I actually
train you and help you uh with your
pronunciation so you can go down and
click on the link in the description
below to sign up for that if you're
interested that's
patreon.com time and of course if you
like this podcast please give it a
five-star rating and write a review and
share it with anyone else you know who's
learning English uh that really helps me
out and it will help them out too all
right let's get started are your ears
ready you know what what time it is it's
listening
time okay let's talk about
pronunciation specifically English
pronunciation and even more specifically
American English
pronunciation so English is one of the
hardest languages to pronounce like a
native speaker uh all languages have
their challenges when it comes to
pronunciation
however if you want to speak like an
American for example and you didn't
learn English as a child that is really
really really hard I can't even uh
emphasize enough how hard that is in my
whole life I don't think I've ever heard
a person who learned English as an adult
and speaks exactly the same way that an
American speaks for example I don't
think I've ever seen that in my whole
life I've seen a couple people who have
gotten close who've gotten very close
actually uh but I don't think I've ever
seen or met a person who sounds exactly
like a native speaker if they learned as
an adult
of course if you learned as a kid or
even as a teenager yeah you can achieve
that level uh many people achieve that
level especially if you learned as a kid
well you can just become a native
speaker of course however I'm talking to
uh you guys who most of you are adults
and you're learning English as a foreign
language and so you have this unique
challenge of learning English as an
adult and trying to improve uh the way
that you speak and your pronunciation so
that's the first thing that I wanted to
mention is that it's really hard to
sound like a native speaker if you're
learning as an adult so the first thing
you need to do is lower your
expectations okay so why is English
pronunciation so hard well the main
reason is because in English stress is
everything stress is King okay English
is what we call a stress timed language
basically what that means is that we
have more or less the same amount of
time between stressed
syllables so even if you have a word or
a phrase where there is a stress
syllable and then three unstressed
syllables and then another stress
syllable that time between the stressed
syllables would be pretty much the
same uh as if you had another word or
another phrase where it's one stressed
syllable one unstressed syllable in one
stress syllable let me give you an
example so if I say the phrase sadly
no uh in that phrase I have three
syllables sadly no so the way I would
say that is I would stress the first
syllable I would have emphasis on sad
not on Le I don't say sadly I say sadly
right
so I stress that first syllable And I
stress no sadly no so stress and then
not as much stress and then
stress and so you can hear that pretty
clearly right however if I say the
phrase
unfortunately
no now I have stress on four
but then all of the next three syllables
after it are all syllables that don't
have a lot of stress and then the word
no is stressed so listen again
unfortunately no so that amount of time
between the for and the no is pretty
much the same as the amount of time uh
in the phrase sadly no that
Lee in the word sad has pretty much the
same amount of time uh that we use to
say it as the last three syllables of
unfortunately so because of that rule
there are many times when syllables are
said really fast and really short so
listen to the two one more time sadly ly
no unfortunately no so you can hear how
fast and how short those syllables are
on the word
unfortunately right so that's an example
of what a stress timed language is so
the opposite of a stress timed language
would be a syllable timed language so if
you speak Spanish for example you speak
a syllable timed language so each
syllable
has a pretty similar amount of time that
it takes to pronounce that syllable you
don't have these big differences in the
length of syllables in English an
unstressed syllable might be
13 or sometimes 1/4th the length of a
stressed syllable that's a huge
difference however in a syllable timed
language like Spanish you don't have
that difference right stressed syllables
and unstressed syllables don't have a
big difference in how long it takes to
say them so that's why if you're a
Spanish speaker for example and you are
trying to uh speak English like a native
it can be very hard to
replicate this stress timing because
you're not accustomed to reducing and
shortening all of these unstressed
syllables that's not something that you
do in Spanish so that's uh the
difference between a stress timed and a
syllable timed language and so in a
stress timed
language when a syllable is not stressed
it can often become reduced so for
example the word f r is usually not
stressed in English so we don't
pronounce that as for we say
for right I say for example I don't say
for
example you hear that there's a
difference so that's an example of how
an unstressed syllable or word becomes
reduced and that happens all the time in
English that happens in virtually every
sentence that we say these words or
syllables that aren't stressed can often
become reduced their pronunciation Chang
changes because the vowel is
shortened okay so that's uh stress in
summary in a nutshell okay that can um
make English a very very difficult
language to pronounce like a native
speaker uh and besides stress there's
also the issue of sounds individual
sounds that can be hard because they're
different in English uh than they are in
your language uh we have different
sounds in English than uh The Sounds in
Spanish for example so besides stress
you also have to deal with these new
sounds that are unfamiliar to you it's
not natural for you to make these sounds
so um um there are other things that are
difficult but really the the two main
things that make English so hard to
pronounce is the stress number one and
number two some of the sounds might be
hard so those are the biggest
challenges that you will face so how do
you improve your pronunciation I just
talked about pronunciation and about the
difficulties with English
pronunciation but now the question is
how do you actually improve in this area
of your English learning well it's
important to note that pronunciation
doesn't improve the same way uh as
fluency or listening or
vocabulary those things improve in a
more natural way and if you've been
listening to me for a long time you
probably know by now that I'm an
advocate of allowing yourself to acquire
the language in a natural way by the way
when we say that you're an advocate of
something we're saying that you support
some idea or something so I'm an
advocate of allowing yourself to acquire
the language naturally mainly through
listening but also reading so when you
listen and you read you acquire
listening skills and reading skills of
course you acquire
vocabulary and you even acquire
fluency because you have full
phrases and
collocations in your brain that you can
reproduce once you've heard them enough
okay so those things improve
naturally however pronunciation doesn't
improve as naturally as these other
elements okay so pronunciation requires
a more concentrated effort in order to
improve it listening will improve your
pronunciation that's for sure if you
listen a lot and if you listen very
intently that will help you improve your
pronunciation no doubt however beyond
that if you want to actually have a big
Improvement in your
pronunciation and improve it
faster then the key uh to this is that
you need to notice your mistakes you
need to
notice the real sounds of English you
notice how native speakers say something
versus how you are expecting them to say
it and once you begin to notice these
things you start to shift
your understanding and your
expectation of what things are supposed
to sound like okay by the way the word
shift just means that you change okay so
when you start to notice these things
then your whole
perception of
sounds and uh this whole element of
English will change you'll start to be
able to identify the difference between
how you say something and how a native
speaker says something okay so um
noticing is key and how do you notice
well this is also something that doesn't
come naturally most of the time it does
to an extent but it's something that uh
comes more with uh practice and training
actually so for example my English
pronunciation seminars and my listening
practice seminars are a great way to
start to notice things because I focus
the whole seminar on showing you
different patterns that you need to
notice
and I help you change your perception of
what things are supposed to sound like
so for example my seminars could be a
great way for you to start to notice
these things and you get those if you
join my membership of course and just
being with a teacher and working with a
teacher who is trained to help you with
with your
pronunciation is another way to start to
notice these things a teacher can point
these things out to you and help you
notice them by the way when we say that
you point something out we're saying
that you uh indicate or identify it so
that the other person notices it so a
teacher can help you do that my seminars
can help you do that and then once
you've been trained a little bit then
you can start to do this on your own and
you can start to uh notice more things
by yourself you won't notice everything
but you'll start to notice more so uh
it's good to get this type of training
to start noticing on your own and when
it comes to noticing and focusing on
mistakes I want to point out that there
are two categories of pronunciation
mistakes so there are mistakes that are
easily noticeable and
fixable and then there are mistakes that
aren't so let me explain this so a lot
of mistakes can be categorized as
mistakes that you can easily notice and
fix if someone points them out to you
you probably won't notice them on your
own but a teacher or my seminar for
example might point it out and then you
can fix it so for example uh things uh
that are related to stress are actually
pretty fixable for example within one
word you might be stressing the wrong
syllable for example the country Japan
in this word the second syllable is
stressed Japan however many English
Learners stress the wrong syllable they
say japen and that's wrong but it's very
easy to notice if a teacher points that
out to you and it's very easy to fix you
just stress the other syllable instead
of Japan you say Japan right it's not
hard so that's an example um and stress
within a sentence for example instead of
saying uh I want it what we would say is
I want it in most cases so instead of
stressing the I we would stress the want
I want it
not I want it right if someone points
that out to you that you're stressing
the wrong word it's pretty easy to
notice that and then to say it correctly
that doesn't mean that you'll say it
correctly next time but in this moment
you can say it correctly and start to
register that in your brain you can
register that error there and maybe
notice it a little bit more in the
future also uh with um skipped syllables
for example in the word family the I is
silent we don't say family we say family
that's something that a teacher can
point out to you and it's pretty easy to
fix just don't say the middle syllable
it's just family like it's not several
it's several you just skip the syllable
so if someone points that out to you
it's pretty easy to fix also certain
letter combinations like the TU can be
pronounced Che sometimes like
situation and du can be with a J sound
like
graduate okay uh or sometimes you're
just saying the wrong vowel instead of
uh saying priority maybe you say
priority and you just need to change the
pre to pry or maybe you say
noice uh but the correct pronunciation
is notice you just need to change the a
to an O notice right uh so those are
examples of fixable errors that are very
easy to
identify uh if you're a trained teacher
uh who can actually teach pronunciation
of course so in my seminars for example
uh I point these things out or other
teachers who teach pronunciation can
easily identify this and uh you can fix
it right however there are other
pronunciation ation mistakes that are
much harder to identify and fix and
these have to do with your accent so
your accent uh refers to um the way that
you pronounce English sounds um based on
the Sounds in your own language so for
example there are certain vowel sounds
in English that you don't have in
Spanish for example so like in the
different vowels in the words hit and
heat that might be hard for you to even
hear the difference right or laugh
versus love or food versus foot those
different vowel sounds in those words
might be really hard for you to
identify and pronounce differently
because some of these are sounds that
you don't have in your language so
because of that it's harder to hear them
and harder to fix them so there are many
other examples that I could give but I
think you get the point right there are
some errors that are not easy for you to
hear and they're not easy for you to fix
and you have to accept the fact that um
you're not gonna get rid of your accent
very quickly that's gonna stay for a
long time and usually it stays forever
but you can reduce it over time but it
takes a long time okay so when it comes
to improving your
pronunciation I would say that you
should focus mostly on the fixable
errors okay the ones that are very easy
to notice and fix and if you fix those
errors you your pronunciation will
improve a lot because there are a lot of
fixable errors however when it comes to
your accent you need to have more
realistic expectations you can also take
classes with an accent coach a
professional who can uh help you with
this but um this is a very
specialized field of course so that's
pretty much what I wanted to talk about
today uh I hope this gave you a good
idea of uh why pronunciation is
difficult in English and how you can
improve it uh and of course remember to
sign up for my membership if you want my
pronunciation training specifically if
you become a super member or anything
higher than that then you get my
pronunciation seminars and even just
with the listening practice seminars
this will also help you with your
pronunciation so if you want my training
make sure to sign up the link is in the
description below this episode that's
patreon.com time and of course sign up
for my new podcast as well if you want
to practice listening with real
conversations that's patreon
on.com USC conversations the link is
down below and if you like this podcast
please give it a five-star rating and
writer review and share it with anyone
you know who's learning English all
right thank you for listening to this
episode and I'll talk to you on the next
episode of listening
time